"Do Alkaline Diets Help
Athletic Performance?"
Theoretically, bathing your muscles in
an alkaline environment should enable
faster acid removal from muscle
cells, delaying the muscle fatigue
that's due to the buildup
of lactic acid in the muscle.
Given these buffering effects,
no wonder sodium bicarbonate —
in other words, baking soda —
has been found to have such
significant ergogenic
or performance-enhancing
effects on muscular endurance.
The problem with loading with
baking soda is that it frequently
causes severe gastrointestinal
distress, and at standard doses
you could easily take in twice the
recommended upper daily limit
of sodium in just that one load.
Therefore, what about a low-acid diet,
which focuses on high intakes
of fruits and vegetables?
That may be an attractive
alternative to bicarbonate loading
for improving anaerobic
exercise performance,
meaning short burst
activity like sprinting.
Today's diets are acid-forming,
meaning higher in animal foods
with fewer vegetables and fruits,
whereas in general, the alkaline-
promoting diet is centered around
whole plant foods, with few processed
foods and less meat, dairy and eggs,
which are accepted as acid-forming
foods. Although alkalizing chemicals
such as sodium bicarbonate have
been shown to consistently improve
performance, alkalizing diets do
not demonstrate the same effect.
A review of ten studies
that investigated
the effect of high versus low dietary
acid loads on athletic performance
did not find consistently improved
exercise performance
at maximal or submaximal
exercise intensities.
However, maybe they just
didn't go alkaline enough?
For example, in this study
they had people eat more
fruits and vegetables
and less meat, cheese,
cereals, and eggs,
but saw no difference in any
performance-related parameters.
But a sufficiently alkaline diet
is characterized by the production
of alkaline urine, a pH
of pee at least 7 or higher.
And if you look at what
the participants achieved,
most failed to meet
the benchmark,
so their diet may just not have
been alkaline-forming enough.
In this study showing enhanced
400-meter sprint performance,
they were able to swap out
enough meat, eggs, cheese
and cereal products, and swap
in enough fruits and vegetables
that they were just barely
able to make 7,
and they did get a little performance
boost, suggesting that it's possible
to improve sprint performance by
consuming alkalizing natural foods
and beverages, without
the ingestion of baking soda.
Thus, an alkalizing diet may be
an easy and natural way
to enhance performance.
However, the performance
enhancement was only about 2% —
just a few seconds.
But check out this study.
The same general strategy:
more fruits and vegetables,
and less the acid-promoting
foods such as meats, cheeses,
and refined grains. But they
weren't messing around.
Six to eight cups of vegetables,
plus more than four
servings of fruit a day, got
their urine up over 7, and a 21%
performance enhancement.
That's extraordinary.
Now this doesn't necessarily mean
it has anything to do with the pH.
I mean they ate more vegetables,
which contain dietary nitrates,
which alone acutely improve
exercise performance.
It's possible that nitrates
might have enhanced
exercise performance
during the low-acid trial.
However, that would entail
extracting more energy
from every breath,
and they didn't find that.
But any time you make huge
changes in peoples' diets,
it's hard to pinpoint exactly what
made the critical difference.
But these extra benefits
are a feature, not a bug.
Because a more alkaline-forming
diet is rich in fruits and vegetables,
and deplete of many unhealthy foods,
a low-acid diet could not only provide
exercise performance benefits, but
might also reduce chronic disease risk.
Any performance benefits
in non-athletes?
The effect of an alkaline diet
on body composition
and aerobic exercise performance
of sedentary women.
A randomized controlled trial,
swapping in vegetable protein
sources like legumes for
animal protein sources, and...
a greater decrease in weight, body
fat mass, lactic acid accumulation,
and perceived exertion levels,
all the while exhibiting a boost
in exercise performance
duration and VO2 max levels,
which is a measure of fitness.
Again pH could just be one of many
explanations why eating healthier
could make you perform
better, but either way
we should recommend athletes
of all ages focus on consuming
ample amounts of fruits and vegetables,
if only to maintain long-term health.